

COPENHAGEN · DENMARK

🛮 (+45) 5360-1352 | 🗷 alexander@herhjemme.dk | 🎢 alrojo.github.io | 🖸 alrojo | 🛅 alexrosejo | 💆 @alexrosejo

Research Interest

I am curious about the underlying latent structure of language. I investigate language through mathematical constructs, bioinformatics, and chemistry. My recent work is focused on building neural components that can extrapolate and transferring natural language processing methods into bioinformatics and cheminformatics. Proteins are the most structurally complex and sophisticated molecules in existence. This structure has been developed and fine-tuned over billions of years of evolutionary history. The language of proteins is structured with many unknown rules of behavior. This makes proteins a interesting vessels for learning latent features.

Education

Technical University of Denmark

M.Sc. Mathematical Modeling and Computation, GPA: 11.44/12.00

- Nanyang Technological University, Singapore Semester Abroad Fall 2015
- · Honors program, Supervised by Professor Ole Winther

Copenhagen Business School

B.Sc. Business Administration and Information Systems, GPA: 10.70/12.00

• Lincoln University, Canterbury, New Zealand — Semester Abroad Fall 2013

Kongens Lyngby, Denmark

Sept. 2014 - Dec. 2016

Frederiksberg, Denmark

Sept. 2011 - Jun. 2014

Experience _____

Technical University of Denmark

RESEARCH ASSISTANT

Kongens Lyngby, Denmark

Inspired by my time at Salesforce Research, I started a student based research lab with research meetings every Tuesday and one-on-ones every Thursday. More than 30 students (M.Sc. and Ph.D.) have participated in the lab in 2019 resulting in several paper submissions. To find research projects I utilize the many professors at the university for ideation and to find interesting datasets. The majority of my students have previously done projects with me in 02456 Deep Learning.

Salesforce

172 University Ave, Palo Alto, CA 94301, USA

DEEP LEARNING RESEARCH, INTERN

Jan 2017 - Jan 2018

Jan 2019 - Present

Under the supervision of Richard Socher (Salesforce Research) I researched in probability based decision making (+100k impression blogpost, ACL workshop paper); multi-task learning for NLP; and mixture-of-experts using distributed computing, PyTorch, and TorchText.

Teaching.

Technical University of Denmark

Head TA

DEEP LEARNING, 02456

Fall 2016, Fall 2018, Fall 2019

In 2018 and 2019 I have been the head TA with significant course material contributions. Half of the course is project based and I supervise the NLP, Bioinformatics, and RL projects; the most popular amongst students for 2018 and 2019.

Co-Supervisor

MASTER THESIS SUPERVISION

Spring 2019, Fall 2019

I co-supervise 11 Master Thesis projects (an M.Sc. thesis is 5 months full-time). The thesis' have investigated formal languages, Levenhstein transformer, multi task learning, exploration in VQA, bio-/, and cheminformatics; resulting in multiple journal submissions.

Co-Supervisor

SPECIAL COURSES

Spring 2019, Fall 2019

I have supervised 10 special course projects (a special course is 4 months part-time). Similar to M.Sc. thesis, the special courses have investigated topics within deep learning methods and applications.

Course Responsible

INTRO REINFORCEMENT LEARNING

Spring 2019

Exercises from Chap 1-13 in Sutton & Barto and Homework 1-2 from UC Berkeley's Deep RL course. 9 Students (M.Sc. and Ph.D.).

Course Co-Responsible

DEEP REINFORCEMENT LEARNING

Jun. 2019

Adjusted version of UC Berkeley's Deep RL course, co-supervised with Ass. Prof. T. Herlau. 10 students (M.Sc. and Ph.D.).

DECEMBER 5, 2019 ALEXANDER R. JOHANSEN · RÉSUMÉ

Community

Deep Learning Copenhagen

MeetUp

Nov. 2018 - PRESENT FOUNDER

Inspired by Richard Socher's public poster exam in CS224N I convinced Professor Ole Winther to do the same for our 02456 Deep Learning course. With students posters, company sponsored first prize, drinks, and pizza. Given the positive feedback, me and a bioinformatics Ph.D. student started a research lab and kept hosting events for our students. This has resulted in seven events by now, +1.5k participants, and multiple company sponsorships. (Event page https://www.meetup.com/Deep-Learning-DTU/ Student research lab https://alrojo.github.io).

Open Source

GOOGLE TENSORFLOW

contrib.seq2seq: #4761, #4686, #4382

TensorFlow tutorial (2k stars): https://github.com/alrojo/tensorflow-tutorial

Academic Reviews

2020	AAAI , Association for the advancement of artificial intelligence	Program committee
2019	CoNLL, Computational Natural Language Learning	Reviewer
2018	CoNLL, Computational Natural Language Learning	Reviewer
2017	NIPS, Neural Information Processing Systems	Assisted review
2017	ICML, International Conference on Machine Learning	Assisted review

Journal Publications

An introduction to deep learning on biological sequence data: examples and solutions

PUBLISHED

BIOINFORMATICS (IF: 4.5) Volume 33, ISSUE 22, PAGES 3685-3690, OXFORD UNIVERSITY PRESS

HTTPS://ACADEMIC.OUP.COM/BIOINFORMATICS/ARTICLE/33/22/3685/4092933

V. Jurtz, A. Johansen, M. Nielsen, J. Armenteros, H. Nielsen, C. Sønderby, O. Winther and S. Sønderby

Conference Publications ___

Deep recurrent conditional random field for protein secondary structure prediction

ORAL

2017

2017

2016

ACM Conference on Bioinformatics, Computational Biology, and Health Informatics

HTTP://DELIVERY.ACM.ORG/10.1145/3110000/3107489/P73-JOHANSEN.PDF

A. Johansen, C. Sønderby, S. Sønderby and O. Winther

A deep learning approach to adherence detection for type 2 diabetics

POSTER

IEEE ENGINEERING IN MEDICINE AND BIOLOGY SOCIETY (EMBC)

HTTPS://IEEEXPLORE.IEEE.ORG/STAMP/STAMP.JSP?ARNUMBER=7471776

A. Mohebbi, T. Aradóttir, A. Johansen, H. Bengtsson, M. Fraccaro, M. Mørup

Epileptiform spike detection via convolutional neural networks

POSTFR

IEEE INTERNATIONAL CONFERENCE ON ACOUSTICS, SPEECH AND SIGNAL PROCESSING

HTTPS://IEEEXPLORE.IEEE.ORG/STAMP/STAMP.JSP?ARNUMBER=8037462

A. Johansen, J. Jin, T. Maszczyk, J. Dauwels, S. Cash and M. Westover

Workshop and Abstract Publications.

Measuring arithmetic extrapolation performance

POSTER

NEURIPS WORKSHOP ON SCIENCE MEETS ENGINEERING OF DEEP LEARNING

HTTPS://ARXIV.ORG/ABS/1910.01888 A. Madsen, A. Johansen

2019

Language modeling for biological sequences — curated datasets and baselines

POSTER

NEURIPS WORKSHOP ON LEARNING MEANINGFUL REPRESENTATIONS OF LIFE

https://orbit.dtu.dk/files/193584092/Learning_the_language_of_life_abstract.pdf

J. Armenteros, A. Johansen, O. Winther, H. Nielsen

Learning the language of life

ORAL

INTELLIGENT SYSTEMS FOR MOLECULAR BIOLOGY / EUROPEAN CONFERENCE ON COMPUTATIONAL BIOLOGY

2019

J. Armenteros, A. Johansen, O. Winther, H. Nielsen

Learning when to skim and when to read

ACL Workshop on Representation Learning for NLP

HTTPS://ARXIV ORG/ARS/1712 05483

A. Johansen, R. Socher

Neural machine translation with characters and hierarchical encoding

NIPS RECURRENT NEURAL NETWORK SYMPOSIUM

HTTPS://ARXIV.ORG/ABS/1610.06550

A. Johansen, J. Hansen, E. Obeid, C. Sønderby and O. Winther

POSTER 2016

POSTER

2017

Current Projects _____

Neural arithmetic units UNDER REVIEW, Ratings: 8/3/6/6

SUBMITTED TO INTERNATIONAL CONFERENCE ON LEARNING REPRESENTATIONS

HTTPS://OPENREVIEW.NET/FORUM?ID=H1gNOEHKPS

A. Madsen, A. Johansen

Autoencoding undirected molecular graphs with neural networks

UNDER REVIEW

SUBMITTED TO JOURNAL OF CHEMICAL INFORMATION AND MODELING (IF: 3.9)

HTTPS://ALROJO.GITHUB.IO/MEDIA/PUBLICATIONS/MOLECULES/PREPRINT.PDF

J. Olsen, P. Christensen, M. Hansen, A. Johansen

Prediction of GPI-Anchored proteins with pointer neural networks

UNDER REVIEW

SUBMITTED TO PROTEINS: STRUCTURE, FUNCTION, AND BIOINFORMATICS (IF: 2.5)

HTTPS://www.BIORXIV.ORG/CONTENT/10.1101/838680v1.ABSTRACT

M. Gıslason, H. Nielsen, J. Armenteros*, <u>A. Johansen</u>* (*equal contribution)

Language modeling for biological sequences — curated datasets and baselines TO BE SUBMITTED

TO BE SUBMITTED FOR BIOINFORMATICS (IF: 4.5) BY MEDIO JAN 2020

HTTPS://GITHUB.COM/ALROJO/UNILANGUAGE/BLOB/MASTER/PREPRINT.PDF

J. Armenteros*, A. Johansen*, O. Winther, H. Nielsen (*equal contribution)

Predicting recombinant gene expression with deep learning techniques TO BE SUBMITTED

TO BE SUBMITTED FOR JOURNAL OF BIOTECHNOLOGY (IF: 3.1) BY MEDIO JAN 2020

H. Martiny, J. Armenteros, <u>A. Johansen</u>, J.Salomon, H. Nielsen

Short term blood glucose prediction based on continuous glucose monitoring data TO BE SUBMITTED

To be submitted for IEEE Engineering in Medicine and Biology Society (EMBC) by 1st Jan 2020

A. Mohebbi, A. Johansen, N. Hansen, P. Christensen, M. Jensen, J. Tarp, H. Bengtsson, M. Mørup

Patents_

Probability-Based Guider PENDING

US PATENT APP. 15/853,530 2017

A. Johansen, B. McCann, J. Bradbury, R. Socher

Deep Neural Network-Based Decision Network PENDING

US PATENT APP. 15/853,570 2017

A. Johansen, B. McCann, J. Bradbury, R. Socher

Technical Skills_

Programming Python, Matlab, SQL, Java

ML Frameworks PyTorch, TensorFlow, Theano, Lasagne, CUDA

Others Linux, Docker, Vim, IPythonNotebook, Google Colab, Git, Github, AWS S3, AWS EC2, ETFX